What's this? It's all squirmy...
うわっ　何だかこれ　うにょうにょしてる！
What's this? An alien umbilical cord?
何ですか？
これは　エイリアンの　へその緒ですか？
You're the one that put it in, you eat it!
どうせ　お前が入れたんだろ
お前が　食え！
No.
嫌です
Young ones, you mustn't waste food.
諸君　食べ物を　粗末にしてはいけない
Ozu, you put chocolate in the damn napkins, didn't you?
小津　てめえ！　茶きんに　チョコ入れやがったな！
Hanuki-san, you put in beer, didn't you?
羽貫さん　ビール入れたでしょ？
バレた？
You caught me?
But it deepens the flavor, don't you think?
でも　味に深みが出るでしょ
It's already so deep I can't tell what tastes like what.
もはや　深過ぎて　何が何の味だか分かりません
すいませんが　一度　カーテンを
開けても　よろしいでしょうか？
I'm sorry, but may I open the curtain for a bit?
しょうがないな
If you insist...
Impressive, as always, Master.
さすがだな　師匠は
Speaking of which, what kind of training is this?
ところで　これは　いったい　何の修行なのですか？
No one knows what the future holds in life.
人生　一寸先は闇である
We must take that endless bit of darkness and turn it to our advantage.
われわれは　その底知れぬ闇の中から
自分の益となるものを
あやまたずつかみ出さねばならない
This is practical training for doing just that.
そういう哲学を　実地で学ぶ訓練だ
Drinking it in the dark, it's not like beer at all.
ふはーっ　暗闇で飲むと　全然ビールっぽくない
羽貫さんは　樋口師匠の下へ出入りしている
謎の歯科衛生士である
Hanuki-san is a mysterious dental hygienist who comes and goes under Master Higuchi.
She lives on ethyl alcohol and Castellas,
好物は　エチルアルコールとカステラで
and has a habit of getting drunk and licking people's faces.
酔うと人の顔を　なめる癖がある
If you're drinking with Hanuki-san, you'd better be prepared for an endless night of hell.
羽貫さんと飲むならば
地獄の　エンドレスナイトを　覚悟するがよい
I was once freely dragged all around Kiyamachi,
わたしは　かつて　木屋町から
縦横無尽に引きずり回され
気が付くと
and when I came to I was collapsed near the Ebisugawa power plant all alone...
独りぼっちで　夷川発電所のそばに
倒れ伏していたことがある
And Ozu was a person without even a single point of praise.
そして　小津は　およそ　褒めるべきところが一つもなく
人の不幸で　飯が３杯　食える男である
He could eat three helpings of people's misfortune.
わたしより１５分早いだけの　樋口師匠の一番弟子であり
Although only 15 minutes earlier than me, he's Master Higuchi's first disciple,
"Arrogant"
"Selfish"
"Lazy"
無意義な暮らしぶりを　謳歌してた
and he takes glory in this meaningless lifestyle.
"Perverse"
Why didn't Akashi-san come?
明石さんは　どうして来ないのですか？
It seems she has a report she can't get out of.
外せないリポートがあるらしい
わたしだって　外せないリポートがあったのに
I have a report I can't get out of too, you know!
Indeed, after neglecting my studies
この　いかにも　不毛なメンツに囲まれて
学問そっちのけで　様々な修行に明け暮れた結果
and spending all day "training" for things, surrounded by these worthless faces,
わたしは　２年間の学生生活を　棒に振った
I have made a complete mess of my first two years of college life.
I have a question that must be put to the person responsible for this!
何故　こんなことに　なってしまったのか
責任者に問いただす必要がある
責任者は　どこか？
Where is the one responsible?
"Will the responsible party come forward!"
hitobito wa atsui kumo ni kao wo kakushiteru
人々は厚い雲で顔を隠してる
Humans hide their faces in front of thick clouds
iki ba no nai omoi wo zutto motte toideiru
行き場のない想いをずっと持って研いでいる
Getting more and more consumed by the feeling of getting nowhere
nani mo nai machi ni umorete mo sore demo ima demo
何もない街に埋もれても それでも 今でも
Even now, they're still buried in the same empty town
tsuranaru uindou ni
連なるウィンドウに
A perfect dream of dolls lined up
narabitatsu ningyou no marui yume
並び立つ人形の悪い夢
on a stretched out window
sore to mo soko ni kakurete
それとも倉庫に隠れて
Then they hide themselves away
fusaidetatte
塞いでたって
so that they can be covered up
hokori dake kabutte mitsukaranai
埃だけ被って見つからない
Wearing only their pride, they still can't find anything
dare no te ni datte furerarenai
誰の手にだって触れられない
They still aren't touched, no matter whose hands they're in
boku tachi no genzai wo kurikaesu koto darake demo
僕たちの現在を繰り返すことだらけでも
If we repeat this moment of ours properly,
sou itsuka kimi to deaou
そういつか君と出会おう
I will meet you someday
sonna hi wo omotte hibi wo ikou
そんな日を思って 日々を行こう
Until that day is here, I will keep on going
ikou
行こう
Going
Then I was a brand-spanking new freshman university student
当時ぴかぴかの大学１回生だったわたしの目の前には
and before me lay open countless doors to that rose-colored campus life.
ばら色のキャンパスライフへの扉が無数に開かれていた
However, at that time I had a bad premonition.
しかし　このとき　わたしは　何やら悪い予感がした
"Disciples Wanted"
この　いかにも　うさんくさい　チラシの向こうに
Because I could not envision
those suspicious-looking fliers leading to some glorious future.
いかなる栄光の未来をも思い描くことが
できなかったからだ
I must not reach out for these fliers!
今すぐ　このチラシを　手放さねば
In fact, I should get as far away as possible!
そして　できるだけ　ここより遠くへ
However, I was not able to escape.
しかし　逃れることは　できなかった
"Disciples Wanted"
With the clairvoyance to pick out fair maidens from the crowds of Gion,
「その千里眼は　祇園の
雑踏から意中の乙女を見つけ
and the devil's ears that let not even the sound of sakura falling into the canals slip past,
その地獄耳は　疎水へ桜の降り散る音も逃さず」
I am Higuchi Seitarou!
「我こそは　樋口　清太郎
来たれ　仙才を秘めたる若者よ」
Come, ye youths of limitless possibility!
よっ！　師匠！！
Yes, Master!
My bad premonition was right on the mark.
わたしの悪い予感は　的中した
I held a position of not opening up my heart to anyone,
決して　心を許すまいと　構えていた　わたしだったが
But as Master Higuchi lived in Yuusuisou, the same boarding house as I, we hit it off,
樋口師匠が　自分と同じ下鴨幽水荘に
住んでいると聞いて　意気投合し
and the fact that I was just old enough to drink helped immediately...
"'Myself' is over 20 years old.
Ozu did not imbibe."
酒を飲める年に　なったばかりなのも手伝い
Before long the walls came down and I was enjoying myself.
やがて　大いに　羽目を外していった
And as a result of our heated arguments over boobs until dawn...
そして　明け方まで　乳について
熱い論争が交わされた揚げ句…
The question is not whether it is real breast or not.
本物の乳であるか　偽物の乳かが問題ではない
信じるか　信じないかだ
What matters is whether you believe it.
Switch, on!
スイッチ　オン
One, two, three!
ワン　ツー　スリー
...I ended up becoming his second disciple.
そうして　わたしは　師匠の二番弟子となった
Of course that was the only time our Master ever treated us to alcohol.
師匠から酒を　おごってもらったのは
もちろん　その一度きりである
Being the disciple of Higuchi Seitarou...
樋口　清太郎の弟子
それが何の弟子であるかは
２年たっても　明らかにならなかった
I'm still not clear as to what I'm a disciple in even after these two years.
And if you looked under the cover,
そして　ふたを開けてみれば
Master Higuchi was no hermit-master or anything, but just some eighth-year student.
樋口師匠は仙人でも何でもなく
単なる　大学の８回生であった
ただ　長生きした動物が
神秘的気配を身に付けるように
Like how animals that live long lives feel somewhat uncanny,
our master had this mysterious air about him unlike a normal person's.
師匠もまた　常人ならざる　雰囲気を　まとっていた
He wore the same yukata and tall geta everywhere he went all year round,
一年中　同じ浴衣と高げたで　どこへでも出掛け
and he knew 100 places to cool off in the summer.
夏に涼める場所を　１００個は　知っている
日本語以外できないのに
He couldn't speak anything other than Japanese
but could converse cordially with people in any country,
どこの国の人とも　誰とでも仲良く話せ
and there were times he perceived things that normal people did not.
常人ではない　感知力を
持ってるように見えるときがある
His body was light, and incredible.
身が軽く　体もすごいらしい
かといって　何らかの行動に出るでもなく
That being the case, he didn't participate in anything,
only focusing intently on living life day-to-day.
ただ　ひたすら　堂々と　暮らすことだけに専念していた
His was a frighteningly gentlemanly manner, perhaps the pinnacle of buffoonery.
それは　恐るべき紳士的態度
もしくは　アホの骨頂である
However, he had a weakness.
ただし　苦手な物もあった
He had library fines.
図書館からの取り立てである
Our Master was being targeted
１年近くも　本を返さない師匠を
by a secret collection organization known as the Library Police.
図書館警察という秘密の
図書回収組織が狙っていた
Helping him escape from them was our duty as his disciples.
逃亡を手助けするのは
わたしたち弟子の役目であった
The fiend!
くせ者だー！
Besides the Library Police, Master also had an ongoing battle with a man named Jougasaki.
それと　師匠は　図書館警察だけでなく
城ヶ崎という男との　本当の戦いを続けていたのだった
What color?
何色だった？
ピンクです
Pink.
Master called this battle the "Masochistic Proxy-Proxy War."
その戦いを　師匠は自ら　「自虐的代理代理戦争」と呼び
And as the name implies, it was a "war" of the tiniest,
その名称からも分かるとおり　戦争というには
いかにも　みみっちい
pettiest, stupidest things you could imagine.
汚い汁を　汚い汁で洗うような
みっともない争いであった
It seems that five years ago there was some deep strife between the two
約５年前　２人の間に　深刻な確執が生まれ
戦いの火ぶたが切られたらしい
which caused the opening shots to be fired.
And we, as his disciples, were wrapped up in this pointless struggle.
そして師匠の弟子である　われわれも　また
この不毛な戦いに　巻き込まれていた
"Glued"
For example, when we had 20 plates of sushi delivered,
ちなみに　すし２０人前が　届けられたとき
he'd invite over a bunch of exchange students for a sushi party
師匠は留学生を集め　悠々と
すしパーティーを開いたが
and me and Ozu would split the bill.
その代金は　わたしと小津が折半した
In short, it was always us who got the short end of the stick.
要するに　割を食っていたのは
常に　われわれということになる
I wondered if wasting my precious youth helping with this stuff was a good thing,
こんな争いに加担し　貴重な青春時代を
無駄にしてよいものかと　思いつつも
but each day and the next I worked hard to pay him back.
今日も　今日とて　仕返しにいそしむ　わたしである
Kaori!
香織！　香織！！
K-Kaori!
Jougasaki is a perverted man the same year as Master Higuchi
城ヶ崎とは　映画サークルを主催する
樋口師匠と同回生の　色男なのだが
and the head of the movie circle,
but it's still uncertain what grudge they have between them.
かつて　２人の間に　どんな遺恨があったかは定かでない
The journey is over.
旅が終わったんだ
"Goal"
これは…
What's this?
In the chaos just after the war in the Pacific,
太平洋戦争直後の混乱期
med students that stole the technique
西尾商店の亀の子束子製法を
盗んだ医科大の学生が
behind tortoise-shaped scrubbing brushes from Nishio Market
created a mystical cleaning weapon from the fibers of a palm that grew in Taiwan.
台湾に生息する　特殊なシュロの繊維を用い
魅惑の洗浄兵器を作りあげた
The tips of the fiber were both stiff and supple;
強靭かつ細やかな繊維の先っぽが
ファンデルワールス力によって
it seemingly used the Van der Waals force to bind dirt particles.
汚れ成分と　分子結合を作り出すらしい
And so this company was put under pressure by detergent makers for fear of losing sales.
ところが　自社の洗剤の売れ行き低下を
懸念した企業から　圧力がかかった
驚異の洗浄力を持ちながら
As its power to clean was considered too great a threat, it was banished to the depths of history;
歴史の闇に　葬り去られてしまったが
However, seems like someone continues to make them even now, in secret.
今も　どこかで　ひそかに　幻のたわしは
作り続けられているらしい
I wish to obtain one of these mystical tortoise scrubbing brushes.
この　幻の亀の子束子を　手に入れたい
"Demachi Futaba Mame-mochi"
This is another part of your training.
これも修行の一環だ
"Shuugoin
Nama
Yatsuhashi"
"Nishimura
Eisei
Boro"
Our master has required many things prior to this, and we were always supplying him.
これまでも師匠は　色々な物を欲しがったが
"Ox-drawn cart of ancient pine"
調達するのは　常に　われわれである
"Ueda Sweets Factory Conpa-Rusk"
"Remembrance of Kamesuehiro"
"Ueno Liquor Shop Tsubame Sauce"
"Nishiri Senmai-zuke"
This is the final test.
これは最終試練だ
Please do whatever you can to get it by tomorrow at noon.
明日の正午までに　それを　何としても手に入れてきなさい
If you don't, you're expelled.
でないと破門だ
Perhaps I thought of it while cleaning the 4.5 tatami room,
おおかた四畳半の掃除でも　思い付いたのであろうが
実現する者の身にも　なってほしいものだ
but it's something I did wish could be made a reality.
The Master's room was so dirty that at just that one glance,
師匠の部屋の汚れっぷりは
深窓の令嬢ならば　一瞥するだけで
卒倒するであろうことを保証する惨状である
a lady of sheltered upbringing would surely swoon. It was a disaster.
"Never heard of it"
かつて地球上に　存在しなかった生命体が
I wouldn't be surprised if it was some life form
"You don't plan to buy anything?"
"Are you makin' fun of me, idiot?"
that had never previously existed on the Earth's surface that secretly evolved.
こっそりと別枠で　進化していたとしても
何ら　不思議はない
"Hey, bring the salt!"
Coming all the way to the Sanjou Bridge,
as it was lunch time, I saw fish and onions lined up.
三条の橋まで来ると　昼間っからねぎまが並んでいたので
いっそ花火でも　打ち込んでくれようかと思ったが
I thought I'd rather shoot fireworks at them,
but I had a feeling like I'd already done that,
そういうことを　かつて　やっていたような気もして
なおさら　言い知れない焦燥にかられた
which made my uneasiness all the more indescribable.
When I came to I had moved to Kiyamachi,
気が付くと　わたしは　木屋町に移動しており
そこでは　まだ日が高いにもかかわらず
and despite it still being mid-day, an old fortune teller was spreading out her eerie aura.
占いの老婆が　ただならぬ妖気を　垂れ流していた
こんな人物の占いが　当たらないわけがない
The fortunes of this creature must surely be spot on.
You're back?
また来なすったか？
What do you mean, back?
またとは　何ですか？
You are unsatisfied.
あなたは不満を　抱いていらっしゃる
大変　まじめで　才能もおありだから
Because you have fiercely earnest talent.
I tip my hat to the old woman's insight.
老婆の慧眼に脱帽
Anyway, I feel there's an opportunity you can't let slip away.
とにかく　好機を逃さないことが肝心じゃ
Grab the opportunity dangling in front of your eyes.
あなたの目の前に
ぶら下がってる好機を　つかまえてごらんなさい
That'll be 4,000 yen.
はい　４，０００円
This is getting more and more abridged.
どんどん　はしょられてませんか？
Our master made us do all kinds of meaningless things in the name of "training,"
師匠は　わたしたちに　修行と称して
無意義なことをさせたが　ほとんど意味不明であった
and most of them made no sense.
I thought a countless number of times, "Why am I doing this?"
あのとき　ああしていなければと思うことは　無数にあれど
And I couldn't help but think, "If only I hadn't met the Master..."
師匠に出会ってさえいなければ
という思いは　ぬぐい去れない
Why shouldn't I just expel myself?
もう　いっそのこと　自主破門されてやろうか
Senpai!
先輩
Akashi-san is a first year in the engineering
department like Ozu, and a younger disciple.
明石さんは　小津と同じ　工学部の１回生であり
わたしの妹弟子に当たる
A mystical tortoise scrubbing brush?
幻の亀の子束子…　ですか？
そんな物が　存在するのかどうかも分からないが…
I don't even know if it actually exists.
弱気なことではいけません
You mustn't give up so easily.
Let us search!
捜しましょう
The old man I'd asked before, who was like a boiled octopus,
先ほど　わたしが訪れたときは　煮だこ同然だった親父が
今度は　かぐや姫を見つけた　竹とりの　おきなごとき
めろめろの　ありさまだ
acted nice like he'd just found Princess Kaguya in a bamboo shoot.
The man who runs a general store in West Kinichiba might know something.
錦市場にある雑貨屋さんが　知っているかもしれません
Perhaps the owner of the general store facing Bukkouji road.
仏光寺通に面した　雑貨屋さんの主人ならば…
The man who runs the old book store over there might know something.
あそこの古本屋の親父さんなら
何か知ってるかもしれませんな
The used utensil shop in Shinkyougoku might know.
新京極の古道具屋は　どうでっしゃろ
明石さんは　実に手際良く情報を集め
Akashi-san was quite skilled at information-gathering,
and narrowed down the location of the tortoise.
たわしの在りかを　絞りこんでいった
そして…
And then.
Excuse me!
すいません　幻の亀の子束子を　捜しているのですが
We're searching for the mystical tortoise scrubbing brush.
Um...
あの　幻の亀の子束子…
Do you know anything about the mystical...
Where did you hear of that?
それを　どこで聞きました？
樋口師匠というお方です
Master Higuchi.
Wait a moment.
少し　待っていなさい
T-That's...
こっ　これが…
Um, how much for it?
あの　お幾らになりますか？
Perhaps I will ask 100,000 yen.
１０万円ほど頂きましょうか
Hell if I'm buying that.
せ…　買うものか
No scrubbing brush is worth 100,000 yen.
たわしに１０万とは　無茶な話だ
It's not something you'd wash in a sink of a 4.5 tatami boarding house covered in sludge.
ヘドロにまみれた　四畳半下宿の
流し台を洗うものではない
Enough. I give up on the scrubbing brush.
もういい　たわしのことは　あきらめる
いよいよ　わたしは破門だ
I'm finally expelled.
That Master is not going to cut the thread so trivially.
あの師匠が　そう　やすやすと
縁を切るわけがありません
わたしからも頼んでみます
I will ask him as well.
「きみと　まるになれるのなら」
If I can become a circle with you...
"At the
public
bath"
T-That's...
あっ　あれは…
Farewell triangle; I'll come back sometime, square.
「さよなら　さんかく　またきて　しーかーく」
Circle X triangle... Always a dead space.
「○　×　△　いつも死角」
The world tends to 4 sides, 4 faces, 5 sides, 6 sides, turkey.
「とかく世は　四角　四面の　五角　六角　七面鳥」
Search for the circle...
「まるを探して　まるを探して」
To learn how not to become a circle...
「まるになれぬの　学ぶため～」
It might be nowhere.
It might be somewhere.
「どこにも　ないかも
あるいは　あるかも」
You don't know either...
On this Kamo River.
「君かもしれぬ　この鴨川で～」
Search for the circle...
「まるをさがして～　まるをさがして～」
Search for the circle.
While I was listening to my Master's song,
師匠の歌を聴きながら
わたしは　ふと師匠が　どこか遠い所へ
行ってしまうような気がした
I suddenly had a feeling like he would be going somewhere far away.
Higuchi-kun and Jougasaki-kun were here earlier.
さっきまで　樋口君と城ヶ崎君がいたのよ
It had been a long time since they'd met.
久しぶりに　２人で会って
Jougasaki-san's pretty cool, isn't he?
城ヶ崎さんって　クールな人ですね
そう？
Really?
I don't think Higuchi-kun is all that different, myself.
本当は　樋口君と　あんまり変わらないけどね
信じられませんな
I can't believe that.
Jougasaki-kun hasn't had any other friends than Higuchi-kun since long ago.
城ヶ崎君は　昔から　樋口君のほかに友達いないから
You know, I think that Higuchi-kun is going to make you his successor.
ねえ　樋口君は　あなたに
自分の後を　継がせようとしてるみたいよ
I've already been expelled.
わたしは　もう　破門になるんです
And I don't think I'm suited to living in such a shrewd manner.
それに　生き馬の目を抜くような
生き方は　わたしには不向きです
It all began when two high school seniors were rivals in love.
それは　高等学校の
学生同士の恋のさや当てが発端だ
It's said that it was a drinking contest with unrefined sake,
濁り酒の飲み比べだった　ともいわれているが
but the details are already lost to the depths of history.
詳しいことは　すでに　歴史の闇の中だ
And so this battle dragged on for a long time,
ともあれ　その争いは長く尾を引き
事が　うやむやになることを　拒んだ
and they refused to let it drop without coming to a conclusion.
So in their utter desperation, they thought up the Proxy War.
そして　苦し紛れに　考え出されたのが「代理戦争」だ
They forgot the reason for the battle's beginning,
その　発端となった　争いの理由は忘れられ
and, without regard to changes in society, passed it down through successors.
社会の動向とは　まったく無関係に連綿と受け継がれた
Technically it's called the Masochistic Proxy-Proxy-Proxy-Proxy-Proxy-
正確には…
…だけどね
Proxy-Proxy-Proxy-Proxy-Proxy-Proxy-Proxy-
Proxy-Proxy-Proxy-Proxy-Proxy-Proxy-Proxy War.
Why are we talking about this?
何で　そんな話を？
You're taking it over, see.
君が引き継ぐからさ
When I came back, there was a bag left in my room I did not know.
部屋に戻ると　なぜか　見知らぬリュックが置いてあった
T-This is...
こ…　これは！
Funds for continuing the Proxy War?
代理戦争を引き継ぐ軍資金か！？
もう　何が何だか分からない
I don't know what's what anymore.
くしくも　あの　たわしが　ちょうど買える額であった
It was precisely the amount of money needed to buy the tortoise brush!
Should I take the Eizan Electric up to Kurama and hide it near Ushiwakamaru?
このまま　叡電に乗って　鞍馬で牛若丸をしのぶか
京阪に乗って黒髪の乙女と　浪速の町を駆け回るか
Or should I take the Kyoto-Osaka and head around Naniwa with some raven-haired maidens?
This was called Mochiguman, and Akashi-san had once told me she had lost it.
それは　明石さんがかつて　なくした
と言っていた　モチグマンであった
５匹で一揃いなのを　１匹なくしてしまったらしい
It seems they come in sets of five and she lost one.
Please grab the opportunity that is dangling in front of you.
あなたの目の前に
ぶら下がってる好機を　つかまえてごらんなさい
"A Dream Date with Akashi-san"
I will let myself be expelled!
自首破門させてもらおう
With this 100,000 yen I should return to the life I deserve!
この１０万円で　あるべき人生へと舞い戻るのだ
ハハハハ　よくやった
You've done well.
これで君は　晴れて　最終試練クリアだ
With this you have cleared the final test!
Perhaps I did everything the Master said these past two years just to see this smile.
わたしは　この笑顔　見たさに　２年間
師匠の言い付けを　聞いてきた　だけなのかもしれない
There is a ceremony now.
これから儀式がある　貴君も　ついてきたまえ
Come with me, you.
Master, I have something important to...
師匠！　折り入って話が…
A dual on the Kamooohashi.
賀茂大橋の決闘だ
代理代理戦争を貴君に引き継ぐ
The Proxy-Proxy War will continue with you.
ああ…　待ってください！
Please, wait!
よう　ご両人
Ah, you two.
I will see this through.
見届けさせてもらうわよ
Okay then, let's go.
よし　行こう
And so the cannons were readied for the decisive battle.
そして　決戦の　火ぶたが切られた
西詰より　城ヶ崎氏が歩いてくる
Jougasaki came walking from the Nishimusubu side.
The two soon met in the center of the Kamooohashi.
やがて　２人は　賀茂大橋の中央で相まみえた
Oh, Akashi-san?
おや　明石さん
Greetings.
どうも
We meet again. How are you feeling?
よく会うわね　具合は　いかが？
Thanks to you, I'm fit and healthy.
おかげさまで　健康そのものさ
So you are one of the Higuchi's?
君は　樋口一門だったのか
Yes. I became his disciple last fall.
はい　去年の秋に　弟子入りしました
And isn't that my disciple, Ozu?
それは　わが弟子　小津ではないかい？
He's my proxy, the one who will succeed me.
ああ　これが　俺の後を継ぐ　うちの代理人だ
お前は　自分の弟子だと　思っていただろうが
You might have thought he was your disciple,
but he was actually my spy, you see.
こいつは　俺のスパイだったわけさ
Did I fool you?
だまされただろ？
Ya got me.
やられたなぁ
師匠　すいませんでした
Sorry 'bout that, Master.
That is unprecedented in the history of the Masochistic Proxy-Proxy War.
自虐的代理代理戦争　史上　前代未聞の出来事だよ
お前は　歴史に名を残す
Your name will be etched into history.
Things sure dragged out for a long time.
今回は　長引いたな
Was it five years? Or more?
５年か…　もっとか？
I've forgotten. It's been a battle of so many years.
忘れたよ
何せ　長い戦いだったからね
Ozu was active in all fields, and despite filming a hit-piece on Jougasaki,
小津は　八面六臂の活躍で　城ヶ崎氏の
暴露ドキュメンタリーを撮る一方
樋口師匠の浴衣を　桃色に染めるという
it seems he also dyed Master Higuchi's yukata pink,
and played the part of a meaningless double agent.
意味不明な　あきれた二重スパイぶりを
発揮していたらしい
So this guy is your proxy?
そっちの代理人は　彼かい？
Yes. Thank you.
ああ　よろしく頼むよ
Wait a second!
いや…　ちょっと待ってください！
Well then, let's do it.
じゃあ　やるかね
ああ
Yeah.
Get it over with already!
さっさと　やって！
The battle started with such a flat phrase.
勝負は　あまりにも　気の抜けた　せりふで始まった
In a moment's breath the two clashed!
息を詰めるような一瞬の後　２人は　激突した！
Let's do it!
いくぞ！
いいとも！
Fine by me!
Rock-Paper-Scissors!
じゃんけんぽん！
Okay, it's over!
はい　おしま～い！
Jougasaki-kun won, so Ozu-kun goes first next!
城ヶ崎君が勝ったから　次は小津君が先攻ね
The weight has finally been lifted from my shoulders.
ようやく　肩の荷が下りたよ
これから　どうするんだ？
What are you going to do now?
I'm leaving on a journey.
旅に出る
Hey, Hanuki. Higuchi is spouting some nonsense.
おいおい　羽貫　樋口が
訳の分からないことを言ってるぞ
For now, I plan on circling the globe once.
取りあえず　世界一周してくるつもりだ
羽貫も一緒に行くかい？
Will you come with me, Hanuki?
君は　英語がしゃべれるからな
You can speak English, right?
Don't be crazy. This is foolishness.
無茶言わないでよ　バカバカしい
You have money?
金は　あるのか？
I have the prize money from the Shimanami Cup.
しまなみ杯の賞金があるからね
You, sorry about this,
but please clean up the room with this.
貴君　すまないが　あの部屋を
これで　掃除しておいてくれ
And so my Master disappeared with the wind.
そして　師匠は　風と共に消えていった
Want to go out for a drink?
飲みに行こうか
おっ　やっと　その気になったかい？
Finally in the mood?
ラブドールに　入れ揚げてるんでしょ
You're the one who spends all that money on your love-doll.
Where did you learn about that?
どこから　その情報を…
Ozu-kun. He tells me everything.
小津君　何でも話してくれるわよ
Why that little...
あいつめ…　いったい　どういうやつなんだ
What is his real story anyway?
No!
あっ！？　嫌だ～！
I thought I might rather jump into the Kamo River.
いっそ　一思いに　鴨川へ飛び込んでしまおうか
京都から落ち延びて　室戸岬で悟りを開いてこようか
Or maybe run away from Kyoto to Murotomisaki and obtain enlightenment.
I look forward to our time together...
「今後とも　よろしく　お願いします」
T-This is...
こっ　これは…
I apologize if you were supposed to bat first.
「そちらが　先攻でしたら失礼」
Let's continue to play nice and dirty.
「これからは　ダーティープレイで行きましょう」
The first shot of the Proxy-Proxy War had been fired.
すでに　代理代理戦争の　火ぶたは切られていた
Being caught by Master Higuchi in front of that clock tower
やはり　あの時計台前で　樋口師匠に捕まったことが
運命の分かれ目であったろう
was surely a turning point in my fate.
もし　ほかのサークルを　選んでいれば
If I had joined some other circle, I would have surely spent quite a different two years.
わたしは　もっと別の２年間を　送っていたに違いない
何より　小津と　出会ってしまったことが
一番の失敗であった
Clearly meeting Ozu was my greatest mistake.
tengoku iku tame mainichi kosotto
天国　いくため　毎日こそっと
In order to go to heaven. Everyday, I quietly
naishou de ii koto shiteta kedo
内緒で　いいこと　してたけど
and privately do good deeds
namida hitohira
涙ひとひら
But a single teardrop
atama kurakura
あたまくらくら
Sends my head spinning
ano ko hasuppa koi dorobou
あの娘　はすっぱ　恋泥棒
That stupid girl, that love thief
watashi kenage ii hito
わたしけなげ　いいひと
I am a good and pure person
kanawanakatta koigokoro
叶わなかった恋心
My longing heart was not fulfilled
kamisama doushite
神様どうして
Why, god?
yurusanakucha koi dorobou
ゆるさなくっちゃ恋泥棒
I must forgive her. That love thief
ano ko tabun ii hito
あの娘たぶん　いいひと
Maybe she was actually a good person
wasurenakucha konna koto
忘れなくっちゃこんなこと
I have to forget all these things
watashi wa tengoku
わたしは天国
I'm in heaven
yurusanakucha
ゆるさなくっちゃ
I have to forgive her!